Register of the Mitrofan Ivanovich Retivov Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Mitrofan Ivanovich Retivov papers
1946-1961
2000C79
Hoover Institution Archives
3 microfilm reels (0.45 linear feet)
Writings, photographs, and miscellany, relating mainly to the medical profession in Russia prior to the Russian Revolution.
Retivov, Mitrofan Ivanovich, 1869-1961
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2000.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Location of Originals
Originals in: Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco.
Biography
M. I. Retivov was educated as a doctor. He served in various positions of responsibility prior to the Revolution: as director of the medical section of the Khar'kov workers' disability insurance company, as an organizer of sanatoria for tuberculosis patients in South Russia and the Caucasus, and as vice-president of the Pirogov medical conventions held in Moscow, St. Petersburg and Novocherkassk. Many of his writings are of an autobiographical character and describe his own life as a medical student as well as meetings with other members of the medical profession in pre-Revolutionary Russia.
During the Civil War, he served as chief doctor of one of the largest hospitals (1500 beds) in Khar'kov. Emigrating abroad following the Civil War, he served as a Red Cross doctor in Paraguay in 1932, during that country's war with Bolivia. He died on 19 March 1961 at the age of 92 in Olegario Victor Andrade, Argentina. Retivov's son Georgii was one of the founding members of NTS.
Chronology
1869 Born, Russia
1901-1917 Vice-President of the Pirogov medical conventions in Moscow, St. Petersburg and Novocherkassk
1917-1919 Director of a hospital in Khar'kov, Russia
1932 Major, Red Cross, Paraguay
1961 March 19 Died, Olegario Victor Andrade, Argentina
Scope and Content Note
M. I. Retivov was a prominent doctor in pre-Revolutionary Russia. The collection contain autobiographical and semi-autobiographical writings, including memoirs of the Moscow University medical faculty in the 1890s, and a novel entitled "Moskva studencheskaia," as well as a study of V. I. Lenin and his role in Russian history. Other writings include a brief work on female doctors in pre-Revolutionary Russia.
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming for these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution and the Museum of Russian Culture. The grant also provides depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives. The original materials remain in the Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco, as its property. A transfer table indicating corresponding box and reel numbers is available at the Hoover Institution Archives.
The Hoover Institution assumes all responsibility for notifying users that they must comply with the copyright law of the United States (Title 17 United States Code) and Hoover Rules for the Use and Reproduction of Archival Materials.
Medicine--Russia.; Russia.; Russians--South America.; South America.
- Biographical File, 1957-1961 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Obituaries of M. I. Retivov and his son, Georgii, and a short story by another son, Sergei
- Correspondence (Box 1)
  Fragment of a letter by an unidentified individual
- Writings, 1946-1949 and undated (Box 1-2)
  Holographs of articles, memoirs, book and speeches, arranged chronologically by title
- Photographs, 1940s (Box 2)
  One album, consisting primarily of photographs of family members
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1957-1961 (Box 1)
  - Family file
    - Georgii Mitrofanovich Retivov (son). (Folder 1: 1)
      Obituary
    - Sergei Mitrofanovich Retivov (son). (Folder 1: 2)
      Short story entitled "Ego skripka," Novoe slovo, 1958 February. Holograph
  - Obituary (Folder 1: 3)
- CORRESPONDENCE (Folder 1: 4)
- WRITINGS, 1946-1949 and undated
  - General. (Folder 1: 5)
    Includes notebook containing drafts of letters to the editor, notes, summaries of writings and other matter, including family history
  - "Etiudy o Rossii,", n.d. (Folder 1: 6)
    Holograph. Notebook includes memoirs of medical faculty at Moscow University in the 1890s and an article entitled "Russkie zhenshchiny vrachi," published in Prague in 1942
  - "Ministerstvo Narodnogo Prosveshcheniia vo vremia Dumskoi monarkhii,", n.d. (Folder 1: 7)
    Holograph fragment of a larger work
  - "Moskva studencheskaia,", n.d. (Folder 1: 8-9)
    Holograph
  - "Strannaia devushka,", n.d. (Folder 1: 10)
  - Untitled work on Paraguay, n.d. (Folder 1: 11)
    Holograph. Missing pp. 1-17
  - "Moi vstrechi s russkimi liud'mi ottuda," lecture read before a meeting of the Russian colony at Asuncion, Paraguay, 1946 December 15 (Folder 1: 12)
  - "Vladimir Il'ich Ul'ianov-Lenin,"., 1949
    - Notes. (Folder 1: 13)
      Includes background materials, bibliography, plans and summaries of work
    - Fragmentary drafts (Folder 1: 14)
    - Preliminary complete draft (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - Final draft (missing chapter XII) (Folder 2: 2-4)
- PHOTOGRAPHS, 1940s (Folder 2: 5)
  One album consisting primarily of family photographs